Guide to the William Blathwayt Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Blathwayt papers
1646-1796
1668-1703
OSB MSS 2
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.96
(13 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, newsletters, diplomatic papers, and reports documenting Blathwayt's career and English foreign policy and history in the late 17th and early 18th centuries.
Other Storage Formats: Oversize
Blathwayt, William, 1649?-1717
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase, 1970-74. Each folder contains provenance information that can be used to track down specific purchase data in the files of the curator of The James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Papers in box 12, folder 248 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
WILLIAM BLATHWAYT (1649?-1717)
William Blathwayt, civil servant and politician, was probably born in 1649, the only son of William Blathwayt of St. Martin's-in-the-Fields and Anne Povey Blathwayt. Blathwayt entered public life as clerk in the embassy of Sir William Temple at The Hague, 1668-72. This duty was followed by a grand tour of Germany and Italy. From 1675-79 he served as clerk in the Plantation Office and he became secretary to the Lords of Trade in 1679, a position held until 1696. In May 1680 Blathwayt was appointed surveyor and auditor general of Plantation Revenues. He was the first person to hold this office, one that he retained until his death in 1717. He also served as secretary to the Earl of Conway, Secretary of State for the Northern Department, 1681-83, and purchased the office of Secretary at War in August 1683. In June 1688 he was a reluctant witness in the trial of the Seven Bishops and as late as November 1688 loyally served James II.
His offices were renewed by William III in 1689 and from 1692-1701 he attended William during his campaigns in the Low Countries. Between 1693 and 1710 Blathwayt represented the constituency of Bath in the House of Commons. He also served on the Board of Trade 1696-1707. Although his offices were renewed again with the accession of Queen Anne, he gradually lost them during her reign. He was dismissed as Secretary at War in 1704, was dismissed from the Board of Trade in 1707 with the return of the Whigs to power, and lost his seat in Parliament in 1710 because he had offended to Duke of Beaufort, the man who controlled Gloucestershire.
Blathwayt married Mary Wynter of Dyrham Park in December 1686 and the couple had two sons before her death in November 1691. William Blathwayt died at Dyrham Park on August 16, 1717.
For additional biographical information, see: Gertrude Ann Jacobsen, William Blathwayt: A Late Seventeenth Century English Administrator (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1932).
Scope and Contents
The William Blathwayt Papers consist of twelve boxes of correspondence and related historical and diplomatic papers that document Blathwayt's career and late seventeenth- and early eighteenth-century English foreign policy and history. The papers span the years 1646-1796, but the bulk of the material covers the period 1668-1703.
The bulk of the William Blathwayt Papers consists of materials that were separately cataloged at Beinecke Library. These catalog entries have been essentially reproduced in the box and folder list. Copies of catalog cards have also been placed next to the materials they describe. Many of the original cards describe single documents (for example, the letters of Alexander Stanhope and Robert Yard), but others cover groups of materials. Some items that lacked cataloging have been given descriptions in the box and folder list, but not all documents. Several William Blathwayt letters to George Stepney and Robert Yard are not described individually in the box and folder list.
Series I, Correspondence (Boxes 1-10) holds correspondence and other papers spanning the years 1646-1796, but more than 92 per cent of the documents cover a 13 year period from 1691 to 1703. Some 79 per cent of the letters and papers date from the years 1692-1701, when Blathwayt attended William III on the continent. In addition to English, the collection contains a significant proportion of letters and documents written in French with successively lesser quantities in Dutch, German, Latin, Italian, Spanish, and Portuguese.
The collection contains a seventeenth-century copy of a 1575 letter of William Cecil, Lord Burghley, concerning the possibility of a French marriage for Queen Elizabeth (Box 2, folder 48), but the earliest dated document is a 1646 proclamation for a Lenten fair by Charles I (Box 4, folder 83). Other early documents include an address from around 1667 accusing Lord Clarendon of taking bribes and participating in a treasonous plot (Box 1, folder 1), a 1670 Catholic list of proscribed and controversial works, Edward Backwell's defense against charges of corruption in a 1673 Parliamentary by-election, a small group of 1680-81 letters of Thomas Martyn concerning conditions in Jamaica, a February 1683 letter of Hendrik Brill reporting the death of Lord Shaftsbury in Amsterdam, and two Nathaniel Bacon, the younger, letters to Blathwayt discussing conditions in Virginia.
The Blathwayt Papers contain a number of interesting documents dating from the reign of James II and the Glorious Revolution. They include a ca. 1687 defense of the Established Church and the penal laws (Box 3, folder 54), a June 1688 "List of the Jury for the Seven Bishops" (Box 1, folder 3), 1688 letters from Edward Scott of Guernsey reporting disaffection with the policies of James II, an August 1688 resignation letter from Thomas Sprat, the Bishop of Rochester, to the Ecclesiastical Commission because of his unwillingness to sit in judgment of those who refused to read the Declaration of Indulgence, and a declaration of Parliament dated February 12, 1688/89 stating the reasons why the English throne was vacant and offering it to William and Mary (Box 4, folder 81). For other documents covering the same period, see the headings for Nathaniel Crew, Bishop of Durham; Great Britain, Catholics (Box 4, folder 76); Great Britain, sovereigns, James II (Box 4, folder 83); Francis Gwyn; Sir Thomas Haggerston; Colonel John Hales; Anthony Heyford; and Jesuits. Letters of Mathew Plowman and Stephanus Van Cortlandt give reports of Leisler's Rebellion in New York.
The papers covering the period 1691-1703 primarily document English participation in the War of the Grand Alliance, the uneasy peace from the time of the Treaty of Ryswick in 1697 to the death of Charles II of Spain, the early stages of the War of the Spanish Succession, and domestic politics.
Blathwayt's own letters are found in Boxes 1-2, folders 12-45. Many were written from the continent, mostly from The Hague and Loo, but also from such locations as Dieren, Goer, Loestdike, and "Before Namur." Major correspondents include Lord Galway, the Marquis de Ruvigny, commander-in-chief of English forces in Savoy during the War of the Grand Alliance; the Duke of Shrewsbury, Secretary of State for the Southern Department, 1695-98; James Vernon, Secretary of State for the Northern Department, 1697-1700; Robert Yard, a secretary of state at Whitehall; and George Stepney, Envoy Extraordinary to the Emperor in Vienna, 1702-06.
Blathwayt was the recipient, however, of the great majority of the papers in Series I. One group of correspondents, writing from England, commented primarily on politics, international affairs, and war-making during the reign of William III. A few letters also discussed events in Ireland, the North American colonies, and West Indies. For the period of the War of the Grand Alliance, important correspondents included George Clarke, Blathwayt's deputy secretary of war; Sidney Godolphin, First Lord of the Treasury; Henry Guy, secretary to the treasury; William Jephson, another treasury employee; James Vernon; and Robert Yard. Vernon's 1697-99 letters were particularly newsworthy, containing information on meetings of Parliament, the affairs of government, illnesses and deaths, events in North American and the West Indies, and of pirates in the East Indies and North America. Some half dozen 1699 letters contain references to Captain Kidd. Major correspondents for the years 1701-03 were Sir John Gibson, Lieutenant Governor of Portsmouth; Sir Charles Hedges, an admiralty court judge; William Lowndes, Guy's successor as secretary to the treasury; and Yard.
Diplomats and military commanders comprise the second major group of correspondents for the years 1691-1703. The collection contains extensive runs of letters from the Graf von Friesen, Commander-in-Chief of the English and Dutch forces on the Upper Rhine during the War of the Grand Alliance and Lord Galway, the Marquis de Ruvigny. English and Dutch diplomats represented include Sir Lambert Blackwell, English envoy at Leghorn, Genoa, and Tuscany; John Butts (Helsingör); C. V. Heemskerck, Dutch envoy to the Ottoman Empire; Richard Hill, Envoy Extraordinary in Flanders; Hugh Hughes, English representative to the Imperial Diet at Ratisbon; Thomas Kirke (Genoa); Baron Paget, English envoy to the Ottoman Empire; Edmund Poley (Turin); Sir Paul Rycaut (Hamburg); Alexander Stanhope (Madrid); George Stepney (the German states and Vienna); and Albert Van der Meer, Dutch envoy to the court of Savoy. The letters of Galway, Poley, and Van der Meer provide information on the Italian theatre of operations in the War of the Grand Alliance and the treachery of Victor Amadeus, Duke of Savoy. The letters of Alexander Stanhope from Madrid are particularly useful for the material they contain on the declining health of Charles II of Spain and the Spanish succession question.
The collection holds little material documenting the period from 1704 to Blathwayt's death in 1717 and just a handful of later papers, such as a genealogical account of the Helvin family from around 1770 and the 1781 will of the Countess of Orford.
Series II, Diplomatic Papers (Box 11), contains documents written in French, English, Latin, Dutch, and Spanish. Many date from the time when Blathwayt served as clerk to Sir William Temple, English ambassador to the Dutch Republic, between 1668 and 1672. A handful are in the hands of Blathwayt and Temple. A draft of a 1669 Blathwayt letter, for example, requests information about books published on the recent Anglo-Dutch war. A second group of papers dates from the time that Blathwayt was secretary to the Earl of Conway from 1681 to 1683. The series also includes late seventeenth-century English and Dutch copies of a 1599 commission to Sir Francis Vere (1560-1609) as commander of all English forces in the United Netherlands.
Box 12 holds Oversize papers from Series I and Series II and one folder of Restricted Fragile Papers.
Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697; Pirates; Spanish Succession, War of, 1701-1714; Great Britain -- Colonies -- America; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- 1660-1714; Great Britain -- History -- 1660-1714; Great Britain -- Officials and employees; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1660-1714; Italy -- History -- 17th century; Netherlands -- History -- 1648-1714; North America -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Savoy (France and Italy) -- History; Spain -- History -- Charles II, 1665-1700; Diplomats -- Great Britain; Victor Amadeus, King of Sardinia, I, 1666-1732; William, King of England, III, 1650-1702; Blackwell, Lambert, Sir, -1727; Blathwayt, William, 1649?-1717; Butts, John; Clarke, George, 1661-1736; Friesen, Julius Heinrich, Graf von, 1657-1706; Galway, Henri de Massue, Earl of, 1648-1720; Gibson, John, Sir, 1636-1717; Godolphin, Sidney Godolphin, Earl of, 1645-1712; Guy, Henry, 1631?-1711; Hedges, Charles, Sir, 1649 or 1650-1714; Heemskerck, Coenraad van, 1646-1702; Hill, Richard, 1656?-1727; Hughes, Hugh, fl. 1691-1692; Jephson, William, fl. 1690-1691/; Kirke, Thomas, 1650-1706; Lexington, Robert Sutton, Baron, 1594-1668; Lowndes, William, 1652-1724; Marlborough, John Churchill, Duke of, 1650-1722; Meer, Albert van der; Paget, William Paget, Baron, 1637-1713; Poley, Edmund, 1655-1714; Rycaut, Paul, Sir, 1628-1700; Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718; Stanhope, Alexander, 1639-1707; Stepney, George, 1663-1707; Vernon, James, 1646-1727; Yard, Robert; East India Company; Great Britain. Army; Great Britain. Board of Trade; Great Britain. Lords Justices; Great Britain. Parliament; Great Britain. Royal Navy; Great Britain. Treasury
- Correspondence, 1646-1796; Series I; 4.0' (10 boxes)
  - Address
    - "An Addresse of a Commoner of this Nation in Answer to that of the Earle of Clarendon", [ca. 1667] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Accuses Clarendon of taking bribes in exchange for political favors. He is supposed to have arrogated absolute authority over the Privy Council. The address alleges that the Earl first gave money to the Dutch to avoid war and then provoked war in expectation of personal financial gain. He is also accused of arbitrarily refusing to seal grants and pardons and of participating in a treasonous plot. 1. Clarendon, Earl of. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations-- Netherlands. 3. Great Britain-- Foreign relations--France.
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Oversize, Box 12, folder 231
  - Aldworth, Richard
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, Dublin Castle, 1696 May 14
      Reporting the illness of Lord Capel; the docket appears to be in the hand of James Vernon 1. Capel, Henry Capel, Baron, d. 1696. 2. Vernon, James, 1646-1727.
  - Allcocke, George
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Waltham, 1702 Jul 9
      Writing as constable of Waltham, Leicestershire, to recover a debt for quartering soldiers. 1. Great Britain. Army.
  - Anonymous
    - Letter (in Dutch) to William Blathwayt, Vienna, 1683 Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      "My Heer het Hoff Canceliershop is tot data..." Letter is secret.
  - Anton, Ulrich, duke of Brunswick-Wolfenbüttel, 1633-1714
    - Letter, copy (in German) to Jacob Hop, Wolfenbüttel, 1693 Apr 11
      Concerning the provision of troops for the Grand Alliance; accompanied by a copy of a reply to the Emperor on a similar subject, also signed by Rudolf August. Hop was the Dutch envoy in Denmark. 1. Hop, Jacob. 2. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697. 3. Holy Roman Empire, Sovereigns, etc., 1650-1705 (Leopold I). I. Rudolf August, Duke of Brunswick-Wolfenbüttel, 1627-1704.
  - Arran, Charles Butler, 2nd Earl of, 1671-1758
    - ALS to Edward Southwell, Camp at Promele, [1697] Jun 10
      Making arrangements for a loan and reporting on conditions in his camp. 1. Southwell, Edward, 1671-1730. 2. Great Britain. Army.
  - Arselliers, Gaspard Perrinet Arselliers, Marquis of
    - 2 ALS (in French) to [William Blathwayt], Geneva, 1696 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Concerning payment of his expenses, 1702 Apr 21
      - as English representative in Geneva, and military matters. 1. Spanish Succession, War of the, 1701-1714.
  - Astry, Samuel, Sir
    - "List of the Jury for the Seven Bishops", 1688 Jun
  - Atkinson, Samuel
    - LS to [William Blathwayt], Transport Office, 1698 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Report of a demurage claim to the Transport Office for the ship John & William detained in Newfoundland. A copy of the claim, signed by the ship's owners, is enclosed. 1. Great Britain. Commissioners for Transport.
    - 6 ALS and 1 LS to William Blathwayt, Portsmouth, 1702 Dec 31-
      - Reporting as one of the Transport, 1702/3 Jan 25
      - Commissioners on the embarking of, n.d.
      - Col. Colenbine's regiment to the West Indies. 1. Great Britain. Commissioners for Transport. 2. Colenbine, Ventris. 3. Great Britain. Navy.
    - LS to William Blathwayt, Harwich, 1702/3 Mar 4
      Reporting on transport ships in Harwich 1. Great Britain. Commissioners for Transport.
  - Augustus II, King of Poland, 1670-1733
    - LS (in Latin) to William III, Varsavia, 1700 Jun 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Concerning subsidies for Poland. 1. William III, King of Great Britain, 1650-1702. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Poland.
  - Autel, Comte d'
    - Military orders, copy, for General Flemming, Zulpich., 1693 Jun 22
      Reports on enemy troop movements and size in the region of the villages of Hochscheid, Langenfeld, and Winterfelt. 1. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1688- 1697.
  - Avaux, Jean-Antoine de Mesmes, Comte d', 1640-1709
    - Memoir, copy, presented to the States General, 1684 Jun 5
      Writing as envoy of France about re-establishing peace with Spain after the levelling of Luxembourg. 1. Netherlands (United Provinces, 1581-1795), Staten Generaal. 2. France--Foreign relations-- Netherlands.
  - Aylmer, Matthew Aylmer, baron, d. 1720
    - ALS to [William Blathwayt?], n.p., 1698/9 Jan 2
      "Sr. I wase to wait one you today with Capn. Norris..."
  - Backwell, Edward, d. 1683
    - 3 documents relating to the disputed by-election in Wendover, Bucks., [1673] (Box 1, Folder 6)
      In the by-election for Wendover, Bucks, on 1673 Jan 29, Thomas Wharton petitioned against the return of Backwell to Parliament. These three documents outline Backwell's defense against possible charges of corruption. 1. Wharton, Thomas Wharton, 1st Marquis of, 1648-1716. 2. Great Britain. Parliament, 1673. House of Commons. 3. Elections--Wendover, Bucks.
      See: Oversize, Box 12, folder 232
  - Bacon, Nathaniel, the younger
    - ALS to [William Blathwayt], Virginia, 1683 Jul 10
      Sending Blathwayt his £100 salary and blaming the delay in accounts on the trouble in disbanding soldiers and in putting down "a Parcell of Riotous persons" involved in tobacco cutting. 1. Virginia--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.
    - LS, with holograph postscript, to William Blathwayt, Virginia, 1685 Jun 20
      Approves of the king taking over Lord Colepeper's southern grant; discusses payment of his, Colepeper's, Blathwayt's, and Povey's salaries; mentions the forfeiture of estates by those convicted in "Their Rebellion." 1. Virginia--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775. 2. Colepeper, Thomas Colepeper, 2nd Baron, 1635?-1689. 3. Povey, John, d. 1705.
  - Bagalaar, Giacomo
    - 5 ALS and 1 L (copy, in Dutch) to [Albert Van der Meer], Genoa, 1695 Jul 19- (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Newsletters from Genoa, Sep 6
      - 1. Van der Meer, Albert. 2. Newsletters.
  - Ballerna, Giles
    - ALS (in Italian) to Baron Meyrens, Genoa, 1695 Aug 27
      Concerning the repayment of a bill. 1. Meyrens, Sebastian, Baron.
  - Ballianis, envoy of Mantua
    - ALS (in French) to the Count Galeazzo Boselli, n.p., 1701 Jan 27
      Expressing his support for Boselli, who was detained in the Bastille. 1. Boselli, Galeazzo, conte.
  - Barwick, Samuel
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Bow, 1707 Jun 17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Sending a draft memorial of a warrant for him to receive half of the embezzled prize goods in his position as Casual Receiver in Bow; the Duke of Beaufort's tiles have arrived. 1. Beaufort, Henry Somerset, 2nd Duke of, 1684-1714.
  - Beaver, George
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Deal, 1702 Nov 28
      Acknowledging orders to march his four companies to Deal; Beaver was an officer in Brigadier Seymour's regiment. 1. Great Britain. Army.
  - Berkeley, Charles Berkeley, 2nd Earl of, 1649-1710
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, The Hague, 1693 Aug 26
      Concerning some ships seized by the English and claimed by the Portuguese; letter is signed Dursley. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations --Portugal.
    - Letter (extract) to [Sir John Trenchard], Dieppe Bay, 1694 Jul 13
      Account of the burning of Dieppe. This copy was prepared for William Blathwayt; the original is described in C.S.P.O. 1694-95, p. 223. 1. Trenchard, John, Sir, 1640-1695.
  - Bisset, William
    - ALS to Samuel Lynn, London, 1702 Dec 1
      From Captain Bisset of Brigadier Seymour's regiment, desiring Sandwich and Deal for the quarters of their four companies until they are shipped. 1. Lynn, Samuel, d. 1737. 2. Great Britain. Army.
  - Blackwell, Lambert, Sir, d. 1727
    - 2 LS to [William Blathwayt], Livorno (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Writing as English Consul at Leghorn, 1695 Jul 18
      - about Russell's fleet and other, Sep 19
      - matters. 1. Orford, Edward Russell, Earl of, 1653-1727.
    - 2 ALS and 1 LS to William Blathwayt, Livorno, Venice, London, 1695/6 Jan 23-
      - Sending wines for Blathwayt and the, 1696 Sep 8
      - king, reporting ship movements, and recommending John Burrow as his replacement as English Consul in Leghorn. 1. Burrow, John.
    - 8 ALS to William Blathwayt, Genoa
      - Reporting his audience with the Doge, 1697/8 Jan 5-
      - and the lavish entertainments, Feb 22
      - provided by the Republic of Genoa upon their recognition of William III. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations --Genoa.
    - 5 ALS to William Blathwayt, Genoa (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Concerning his efforts as English, 1697/8 Mar 1-
      - envoy to redress the English, Mar 29
      - grievances against the Republic of Genoa for imprisoning two men for a small debt, misuse of Consul Kirke's money at the Bank of St. George, and constraints on English merchants. Accompanied by attestations of the two English prisoners, dated 1698 Mar 17, and of Consul Kirke and six merchants, three copies, dated 1698 Mar 22. Also present is a copy of the reply of the Senate of Genoa to these grievances. 1. Kirke, Thomas, 1650-1706. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations --Genoa.
    - 7 LS and 5 ALS to William Blathwayt, Livorno, Florence, 1698 Apr 14-
      - Reporting as Envoy Extraordinary in, Jul 22
      - Tuscany his audience with the Grand Duke and his efforts to free one Plowman accused of privateering and other English prisoners, and sending information about wines and Blathwayt's order of six tons of marble for his tomb and paving stones. He also comments on English reservations with Genoa. Enclosed in the letter of July 8 is a copy of the Grand Duke's letter to William III, 1698 May 15, concerning Blackwell. 1 Great Britain--Foreign relations --Tuscany. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Genoa. 3. William III, King of Great Britain, 1650-1702. I. Cosimo III, de'Medici, Grand Duke of Tuscany, 1642-1723.
    - 7 ALS and 2 LS to William Blathwayt, Florence, 1698 Aug 21- (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Reporting Tuscan pleasure at the, Dec 23, n.d.
      - English reception of Prince Giovanni Gastone, the state of Plowman's case, shipments of sine and marble to Blathwayt, and his arrears in pay. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations --Tuscany. 2. Giovanni Gastone de'Medici, Grand Duke of Tuscany, 1671-1737.
    - 5 ALS and 13 LS to William Blathwayt, Florence and Livorno, 1703 May 5-
      - Writing as Envoy to the Grand Duke, Dec 15
      - of Tuscany about diplomatic matters, Sir Clowdisley Shovell and the Fleet, on Peter Jarvis, an Agent for Prizes, and sending Blathwayt wine, marble, and music. He also expresses his desire to be Envoy in Venice. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations --Tuscany. 2. Shovell, Clowdisley, Sir, 1650-1707. 3. Great Britain. Navy.
  - Blathwayt, William, 1649?-1717
    - Letter, copy, to Alderman Allen, Whitehall, 1690/1 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Acknowledges earlier letters and gives Allen guidelines for mustering troops. 1. Great Britain. Army. Allen, Alderman.
    - L (copy) to Captain Atkinson, Whitehall, 1702/3 Jan 26
      Explaining the procedure for filling Brigadier Colenbine's regiment. 1. Atkinson, Samuel. 2. Colenbine, Ventris. 3. Great Britain. Army.
    - L (draft) to Sir Alexander Bruce, Whitehall, 169[0]/1 Mar 3